<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Prance's answer to Mrs. Cellier's libel, and divers other false aspersions cast upon him containing likewise a vindication of Sir William Waller from popish scandals, some mistakes in a pamphlet entituled, The narrative of William Boys rectified, and other remarkables : to which is added the Adventure of the bloody bladder : a tragi-comical farce, acted with much applause at Newgate by the said Madam Cellier, on Saturday Sept. 18, instant / faithfully related by an eye-and ear-witness.</title>
            <author>Prance, Miles, fl. 1678-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12013021</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12013021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52465</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52465)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 574:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Prance's answer to Mrs. Cellier's libel, and divers other false aspersions cast upon him containing likewise a vindication of Sir William Waller from popish scandals, some mistakes in a pamphlet entituled, The narrative of William Boys rectified, and other remarkables : to which is added the Adventure of the bloody bladder : a tragi-comical farce, acted with much applause at Newgate by the said Madam Cellier, on Saturday Sept. 18, instant / faithfully related by an eye-and ear-witness.</title>
                  <author>Prance, Miles, fl. 1678-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for L. Curtis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Waller, William, --  Sir, d. 1699.</term>
               <term>Cellier, Elizabeth, fl. 1680. --  Malice defeated.</term>
               <term>Boys, William. --  Narrative of Mr. William Boys.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52465:1"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>PRANCE</hi>'s ANSWER To Mrs. <hi>CELLIER</hi>'s LIBEL, AND <hi>Divers other falſe Aſperſions</hi> Caſt upon him: CONTAINING LIKEWISE A VINDICATION OF Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> from <hi>Popiſh Scandals;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some Miſtakes in a Pamphlet Entituled, <hi>The Narrative of</hi> William Boys, Rectified, and other Remarkables.</p>
            <p>To which is Added the <hi>Adventure</hi> of <hi>The Bloody Bladder: A</hi> Tragi-Comical <hi>Farce,</hi> Acted with much <hi>Applauſe</hi> at <hi>Newgate</hi> by the ſaid Madam <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> on <hi>Saturday</hi> Sept. 18. inſtant, Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Related by an <hi>Eye-</hi> and <hi>Ear-witneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>L. Curtis</hi> upon <hi>Ludgate</hi>-Hill, 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52465:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52465:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Prance's</hi> Anſwer to Mrs. <hi>Cellier's</hi> Libel, and divers other Aſperſions caſt upon him: Containing likewiſe a Vindication of Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller</hi> from <hi>Popiſh Scandals:</hi> Some Miſtakes in a Pamphlet Entituled, <hi>The Narrative of</hi> William Boys, <hi>Rectified;</hi> and other <hi>Remarkables,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAving twice heretofore cauſed ſome Papers to paſs the <hi>Preſs,</hi> I may poſſibly incur ſome Peoples Cenſure for ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing this <hi>Third</hi> time in that kind. My <hi>old Roman Friends</hi> will perhaps cry out, I do it only to raiſe ſome <hi>ſorry Contribution</hi> from the <hi>Bookſeller,</hi> or out of a fooliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light I take in hearing my Name <hi>Bawl'd</hi> about Streets. Theſe (however will be much <hi>more harmleſs Scandals,</hi> than many others they have been pleaſed to beſtow upon me, and yet no <hi>leſs falſe;</hi> for as the <hi>Stationers</hi> are commonly wiſe enough, not to give too much Encouragement; ſo I am as little inclin'd unto, as qualified for <hi>Scribling;</hi> and therefore ſhall not preſume (with their Famous Oratreſs) to perſwade the World, That <hi>every Line of this ſhall be my own Hand-writing;</hi> but this I will aſſure the Honeſt Reader, That he ſhall find nothing here, but what I know and can juſtifie to be <hi>Punctual Truths,</hi> and of which I think my ſelf oblig'd in Conſcience to give a <hi>publick</hi> and more particular Account, for ſtopping the Mouths of ſuch, as make it their Buſineſs to palliate their own <hi>Villanies,</hi> by wrapping me up in a Cloud of <hi>Falſhoods;</hi> or if it be impoſſible to ſilence their <hi>incorrigible Humour of Lying,</hi> yet I hope, at leaſt, by evident Demonſtrations of Truth, ſo to fortifie <hi>impartial Ears,</hi> That they may not henceforth be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Deluſion from theſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> Charmers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52465:3"/>There is ſcarce any thing has given a greater Confirmation of the Reality of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> than their Murdering Sir <hi>Edmund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey,</hi> of which I have made a <hi>Candid Diſcovery;</hi> they had no other way to ſhift off <hi>that Guilt</hi> from their Party, than by Diſcrediting my <hi>Evidence:</hi> But my Converſation having, I Bleſs God (till then) been free from any <hi>Notorious</hi> or <hi>Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Crimes</hi> or <hi>Follies,</hi> wherewith they might reproach me; and it being <hi>unaccountable Nonſenſe</hi> that any man ſhould <hi>own</hi> himſelf concern'd in ſo black and horrid a Crime, if in truth he knew nothing of it, or that he would run the <hi>Hazard</hi> and <hi>Infamy</hi> thereof, meerly to bring himſelf into danger, and deſtroy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were both <hi>Innocent,</hi> and his <hi>Intimate Friends;</hi> and that I Eſpecially (who was never noted for any extraordinary Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) ſhould forge this ſtory, ſo reproachful to that <hi>Church</hi> in which I have been bred, and for which I was ſo fooliſh a <hi>Zealot;</hi> I that had then (and for ought I know have ſtill) two <hi>own Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> that are <hi>Preists,</hi> and one ſiſter a <hi>Nun;</hi> I whoſe <hi>Trade</hi> and whole ſubſiſtance depended upon her Majeſty, and others of the <hi>Roman Catholick perſwaſion,</hi> that under ſuch Circumſtances I ſhould teſtifie ſuch things (if they were <hi>falſe</hi>) would be <hi>Bedlam-Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant</hi> as well as <hi>Helliſh malice.</hi> They therefore concluded, that no falſe Suggeſtion would appear ſo probable, as to give out that what I have declared of that Aſsaſſination, I was compelled unto by <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Torture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſpurious Conceit, firſt begot in Adultery between <hi>Prieſtly-Impudence</hi> and <hi>Lay-Credulity,</hi> being now grown to ſome Bulk, comes the ever-memorable Madam <hi>Cellier</hi> (that notorious <hi>Midwife,</hi> that has brought abundance more <hi>Lies,</hi> than ever ſhe did <hi>Children,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world) and ſhe expoſes the <hi>Bantling,</hi> and licks the <hi>Cub</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to form, and tricks it up with gay <hi>Swadling-Cloaths</hi> of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or in a word (to leave fooling with <hi>Metaphors</hi>) to colour the buſineſs, She offers her ſelf as a kind of <hi>Ear-witneſs</hi> of the force pretended to be uſed to me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> deſigned by this moſt <hi>groundleſs Lie,</hi> are no leſs <hi>various,</hi> than all <hi>advantagious</hi> for the traiterous Conſpirators.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hereby they hope to repreſent my <hi>Evidence</hi> as Invalid or at leaſt <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> as being originally given not voluntarily, but <hi>per dureſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>point</hi> being once gain'd, The Actors and manner of Sr. <hi>Edm. Godfreys</hi> Murder will become <hi>dubious,</hi> and then they may not only <hi>Outface</hi> it for their own Credit, but caſt it upon <hi>Himſelf,</hi> for the <hi>Beggars,</hi> or the <hi>Earl of Danby,</hi> or the <hi>Preſhyterians,</hi> or any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy elſe, for all theſe they have already (though Sillily and in vain) attempted,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52465:3"/>3. Hereby they hope to give <hi>ſome colour</hi> to the belief of the <hi>Sham-Plots,</hi> which they have or intend to ſet on foot, making the World believe that ſome perſons had made it their <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> by undue means, to fix horrid Crimes on the Papiſts, of which they were not guilty, which muſt be in order to ſome ſiniſter deſigns upon the Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which Methods are indeed <hi>only their own</hi> Popiſh Policies and Practices.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A further deſign is not only to <hi>Baffle</hi> the Diſcovery of the Plot, but to bring an <hi>Odium</hi> on the Nation and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in general, as allowing or ſuffering ſuch <hi>Cruelties,</hi> and Proſecuting <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks</hi> on Teſtimonies ſo unduly obtained.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, though I my ſelf am <hi>inconſiderable,</hi> and not worth an <hi>Apology,</hi> but ſatisfyed with <hi>Truth,</hi> could contentedly ſit ſilent and <hi>ſmile</hi> at their <hi>effronted Forgeries,</hi> yet ſince in the conſequences, 'tis a matter of <hi>importance</hi> to the <hi>Safety</hi> and <hi>Honor</hi> of the Nation, I know not how I can diſcharge my Duty to my <hi>Gracious Soveraign,</hi> (to whoſe Mercy I owe my Life) to my <hi>Country,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> (in which by the Divine Grace I reſolve to <hi>live and dye</hi>) if I ſhould not detect this lewd <hi>Scandal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, <hi>Authority</hi> in a late juſt Proſecution of that <hi>Wretched Woman,</hi> hath fitly confuted her Libel, no <hi>Anſwer</hi> being ſo proper for ſuch ſtuff as a <hi>Pillory;</hi> And at her Tryal upon my Oath (which I wiſh Jeſuits, Prieſts, and indeed all ſorts of Papiſts, had that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious reguard</hi> to, as I have, and I hope ſhall ever conſerve) I did fully ſatisfie the Court of the utter <hi>falſity</hi> of any ſuch uſage; yet leſt the Romaniſts and their Abettors, ſhould pretend that ſhe was Convicted only for <hi>other Branches</hi> of her Libel, and Brazen it out (as they are wont) that what I there delivered was but <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Swearing,</hi> I ſhall here by pregnant <hi>circumſtances,</hi> evident <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of known Fact,</hi> her own <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and other <hi>undeniable Arguments,</hi> make ſuch her Story of my being <hi>Racked or Tortured,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be as <hi>empty,</hi> though withal as <hi>malicious</hi> a Fiction, as the <hi>Father of Lies</hi> could invent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. 'Tis well known, (and <hi>Celliers</hi> Libel, <hi>p.</hi> 18. confeſſes, that the <hi>King himſelf told her ſo</hi>) That the <hi>Law (of England)</hi> will not ſuffer any perſon to be <hi>Tortur'd;</hi> 'Tis a thing not allow'd, not us'd amongſt us; How then can <hi>That</hi> be imagin'd to be practiſed upon me, which never was done on any body elſe ſince the memory of Man?</p>
            <p n="2">II. If <hi>Eliz. Cellier</hi> did at the time ſhe mentions <hi>hear ſuch Groans</hi> of Torture, and had ſuch Reaſons to believe they proceeded <hi>from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52465:4"/>me,</hi> why did not ſhe, who was ſo notable a <hi>Buſie-body,</hi> and ſo familiar with <hi>Ladies</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> and perſons of greater Quality (as ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends) give immediate <hi>notice</hi> thereof to His Majeſty, that the thing might have been <hi>inquired into,</hi> the Contrivers thereof and their ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſigns <hi>diſcover'd and puniſht?</hi> Could ſhe doubt a <hi>Fair Hearing?</hi> that were to caſt a moſt undeſerv'd Reflection on His Majeſties <hi>Juſtice and Goodneſs;</hi> For can it be imagined that the beſt and moſt <hi>Gratious of Princes,</hi> would permit, or <hi>Connive</hi> at cauſeleſs <hi>Cruelties</hi> and <hi>Violations of Law,</hi> meerly by a <hi>falſe extorted Teſtimony</hi> to take away the lives of his <hi>innocent Subjects?</hi> Or can we think the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſo deſtitute of <hi>Friends,</hi> that they could not have <hi>Acceſs,</hi> on ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant an occaſion, to that <hi>Soveraign Ear,</hi> which is ever <hi>open</hi> to the Juſt Complaints of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of His Subjects? Their <hi>Intereſt</hi> was too much, and their <hi>Modeſty</hi> too little, to have <hi>forborn;</hi> but rather they would forthwith have filled all the <hi>Court,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> too with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations. At leaſt, why did not this Gentlewoman or ſome of he. Five Aſſociate <hi>Goſſips</hi> come in to weaken my Teſtimoy at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yal of <hi>Green, Bury,</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> then had been <hi>a proper time</hi> for the ſtarting of this Story? But alas! it was not <hi>hatcht</hi> for many Months afterwards.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Libel, <hi>p.</hi> 2. ſays, Cellier <hi>never ſaw the Counteſs of</hi> Powis, <hi>or had any Money from the Lords accuſed, till about</hi> THE LATTER END OF <hi>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY,</hi> (78.) and then ſhe went and told that La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy abundance of ſtrange Stories of Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedloe.</hi> And <hi>after this</hi> (which muſt be ſuppoſed to be in <hi>February at leaſt</hi>) her <hi>Ladiſhip</hi> (Powis) <hi>taking the Priſoners diſtreſſed Condition</hi> (ſo <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably diſtreſſed</hi> that ſeveral of them died with <hi>Over-eating</hi> themſelves, and four or five in a Gang would commonly Tope off a <hi>dozen</hi> or more <hi>Bottles</hi> of Wine in a day) <hi>into her conſideration, there was a weekly Charity erected.</hi> And this <hi>Mother of the Maids,</hi> and <hi>Nurſe</hi> to ſuckling Swearers of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> was made <hi>Lady Treaſureſs</hi> in that Affair. <hi>About this time</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>going to the Priſon to perform theſe Offices of Charity, on Thurſday</hi> Jan. 9. <hi>I din'd in</hi> Newgate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sure the <hi>Holy Father</hi> that forg'd this part of the Libel, had taken too large a <hi>Mornings draught,</hi> elſe he would have laid his Lies a little cloſer. For how does this hang together? She ſaw not the Lady Powis <hi>till the latter end of</hi> January, and after that there was time ſpent in telling of Stories, and <hi>erecting the Contribution of the well-affected,</hi> and yet after all this, comes this <hi>Female Judas with the Bag</hi> to <hi>Newgate</hi> to ſcatter the Charity, and it happens ſtill to be but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifely the 9th of the ſame</hi> January. I would entreat the worthy Author, (whether <hi>Lord,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>Monk,</hi> or <hi>Bawd,</hi> or <hi>all</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to ſoder up this <hi>flaw</hi> in the next Edition.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52465:4"/>IV. She proceeds, <hi>p.</hi> 3. — <hi>About Four of the Clock I came down into the Lodge with five Women, of which three were Protestants, and we all heard terrible Groans and Squeeks which came out of the Dungeon.</hi> — Pray obſerve, there is not <hi>one</hi> of all theſe five Women that has got either <hi>a Name,</hi> or place of <hi>Habitation.</hi> Nor can ſhe ſay they were <hi>Strangers,</hi> for by her own Tale, they were her <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> ſtaid with her three hours after, nay ſo intimate that ſhe could tell <hi>what Religions</hi> they were ſeverally of, a very <hi>difficult buſineſs,</hi> I'll aſſure you, as times go, but undoubtedly they dwelt in <hi>Fairy-Land,</hi> and were ſome of <hi>Queen Mabbs</hi> waiting Gentlewomen, that uſe to walk <hi>inviſible;</hi> or the <hi>Devil</hi> has ſince run away with them; For elſe why were not <hi>ſome</hi> of them, the three <hi>Proteſtants</hi> at leaſt, produc'd in Court <hi>now at her Tryal</hi> to confirm this part of the Story?</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>I askt</hi> Harris <hi>the Turnkey,</hi> &amp;c. Here the Reader muſt note, That the crafty <hi>Gypſie</hi> knew well enough, that this <hi>Harris</hi> was not in a condition to diſprove her, being long ſince <hi>dead,</hi> and therefore of all the reſt chooſes to make uſe of his name. —<hi>We went behind the Gate and liſſened, and found it to be the voice of a ſtrong Man in Torture, and heard, as we thought, the winding up of ſome Engine;</hi>—That was a moſt <hi>lucky</hi> thought, and very pat to the Buſineſs. But when you invented this <hi>Lye,</hi> I'll warrant you never thought of the Engine called the <hi>Pillory.</hi> —<hi>We went to the Turners Shop without the Gate, and ſtood there amazed with the horror and dread of what we heard</hi> — And yet neither the People of <hi>that Shop,</hi> nor any body elſe heard one bit of all this <hi>Tragedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>One of the Officers came running from the noiſe</hi> [but he too, has no <hi>Name;</hi> What! Could ſhe think of never a Servant at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> that has died within theſe two years to father it on?] <hi>One of us caught hold of him, ſaying, O! What are they doing in the Priſon? Officer — I dare not tell you:</hi> [on my word, a very <hi>Civil Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man!</hi> I was afraid he would have anſwer'd, — <hi>D—m ye for a Bitch, what's that to you?</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſtreſs — It's a Man upon the Rack, I'll lay my life on't</hi> [What <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> or whoſe <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> this was, is a <hi>Secret;</hi> but <hi>A Miſs</hi> ſhe was, we have Madam <hi>Celliers</hi> word for't, who has as much <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Experience that way</hi> as any body about Town, her dear Siſter, and fellow-helping <hi>Witneſs,</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Madam Moſely</hi> her ſelf, not excepted.]</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>We heard theſe Groans perfectly to the end of the</hi> Old Baily. What, no further? Why not as well to <hi>Powis-houſe?</hi> For undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this <hi>ſtrong Man</hi> was Tortur'd in <hi>Perillus</hi>'s <hi>Bull,</hi> and had a <hi>Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Trumpet</hi> all the while at his Mouth. —<hi>They continued till near ſeven of the Clock.</hi> So that it ſeems <hi>Cellier</hi> and her five Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52465:5"/>attended three long hours to hear them, which had they been ſo dreadful as to be perfectly heard to the end of the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> what <hi>a fright</hi> muſt they have put all the Neighborhood into, and how many hundreds, nay <hi>thouſands,</hi> in ſo publick a paſſage muſt have been gathered together to inquire the cauſe of ſuch <hi>doleſome out-cries?</hi> yet is there not <hi>one perſon living</hi> beſides this worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman that remembers any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Then a Perſon in the Habit of a Miniſter, of middle sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ment in, and a Priſoner loaded with Irons was brought into the Lodge</hi>— The Incoherence of this part of the <hi>Romance</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently obſerved at her Tryal by my Lord, <hi>Baron Weſton,</hi> how ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd it is to imagine a man that had been three hours or more on the Rack, ſhould preſently be able to <hi>walk,</hi> loaded with Irons too.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. 'Tis evident, That the <hi>Scope</hi> of this Invention, is to abuſe the World into a perſwaſion, that I was thus miſuſed only to force me to own my ſelf privy unto and concern'd in Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi>'s Murder, and to charge it on the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Now therefore, to <hi>Knock the whole Lie o'th' head,</hi> and confute it beyond any poſſibility of Reply, by notorious <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> I ſhall only deſire the Reader to obſerve, That I was taken into cuſtody the 21 of <hi>December</hi> (78) as appears by the <hi>Warrant of my Commitment;</hi> That on the next day, being <hi>Sunday,</hi> I did upon Examination, ſet forth ſeveral particulars of the Popiſh Plot, which I had heard from <hi>Fenwick, Grove,</hi> and others, as that there would very ſhortly be 50000 Men in Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And on the next day, being <hi>December</hi> 23. on further Examination by a Committee of the Houſe of Lords, I made a <hi>Diſcovery of Sir</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundbury Godfry<hi>'s Murder,</hi> and the Perſons that actually Butcher'd him, <hi>viz. Fitz-Girald,</hi> and <hi>Dominick Kelly,</hi> two Prieſts, <hi>Henry Berry, Robert Green,</hi> and <hi>Laurence Hill,</hi> upon which the <hi>three laſt</hi> were apprehended, the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> being brought to <hi>Newgate</hi> the ſame night, <hi>Berry,</hi> the next day, being the <hi>24th,</hi> and <hi>Green</hi> on the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, being <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> as by the Records of their reſpective Commitments (to which I refer my ſelf) does appear.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, on the ſaid <hi>24th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> I gave a large Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before His Majeſties <hi>moſt Honourable Privy Council</hi> of that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Murder and its circumſtances that fell within my knowledge (agreeable in all things to what the day before I had declared to the Committee, and which ſince I have depoſed at the reſpective <hi>Tryals,</hi> and Printed in my firſt Narrative) And for more full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to His Majeſty, and their Lordſhips, did then go to <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet-Houſe,</hi> and ſhew to the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi> and <hi>Clarendon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Southwell</hi> (ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by His Majeſty for that purpoſe) the particular <hi>Rooms</hi> in which the <hi>Martyr'd Body</hi> had for ſeveral nights been Repoſited, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52465:5"/>moſt truly, and at large, is ſet forth in my ſaid <hi>Narrative,</hi> Page 21.</p>
            <p>Since therefore I had, upon my <hi>Oath,</hi> made ſuch a full Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery on the 23d of <hi>December;</hi> Confirmed the ſame the 24th, both by <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>Satisfactory Circumſtances;</hi> And that the Three <hi>Aſſaſſinates</hi> (ſince deſervedly Executed) were, Meerly upon my Information, <hi>all ſecured in Gaol for that Fact, before the 26th of</hi> December; <hi>What occaſion was there to Torture me on the 9th of</hi> January <hi>following, to diſpoſe me to a Confeſſion of that, which I had voluntarily, and ſo effectually made above</hi> 16 <hi>dayes before?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all which (I ſuppoſe) the Vanity, Incongruity, and Utter <hi>Falſhood</hi> of the Story is ſufficiently apparent, and from thence no leſs plain, That as the Papiſts have a moſt <hi>Wicked Cauſe</hi> to Manage, viz. <hi>Treaſon and Murder;</hi> ſo they make no Scruple at all of Forging and Aſſerting any kind of <hi>Lies</hi> that may ſerve their Intereſts therein; And the more Groundleſs and <hi>Improbable</hi> ſuch their Lies are, with ſo much the greater <hi>Aſſurance</hi> do they Print, and Brazen them out to the World, to make them Credited.</p>
            <p>Yet is not this Slander of <hi>Torture</hi> any New Stratagem; but hath been us'd oft and long ago by <hi>Popiſh Libellers.</hi> For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in one of their Pamphlets Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1602. (but ſaid to be Written in the year 1599.) Intituled, <hi>An Apology of</hi> T.F. <hi>and other Catholicks.</hi> Deſigning, to Out-face the <hi>Treaſon of Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Squire</hi> againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for which he had been Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally Convicted and <hi>Executed;</hi> The Contents of the Third Chapter run thus— <hi>Of the Cruelty of the Rackmaſters in England.</hi> As if Racking of Men were as common amongſt us as in the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> and that Torturers here kept their ſetled Ordinary Offices, and <hi>Commenced Maſters in the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> And preſently after he ſayes— <hi>And may it pleaſe you to conſider, the Barbarous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage and Tyranny that the Rack-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, Tormentors, and Inferior Officers and Examiners, have uſed in the Cauſes of Catholicks for many years, and daily do uſe, obſerving no order of Justice, nor form of Law</hi>— And, <hi>Chapter the Fourth,</hi> he has theſe words—<hi>They</hi> Torment <hi>the Catholicks on bare Suſpitions without any Proof, or</hi> Witneſs in the World, <hi>and that with ſuch Extremity, as they</hi> Lame <hi>ſome, and</hi> Kill others, <hi>and with ſuch Devilliſh Deviſes, as amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans hath not been heard of.</hi> And then to make ſuch his Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Aſſertions the better ſwallowed, proceeds thus— <hi>It is not many years</hi> [but pray obſerve, he dares not ſay for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52465:6"/>fear of a Detection, <hi>When,</hi> or <hi>Where</hi>] <hi>that</hi> Francis Dickenſon, <hi>Prieſt, was taken and Committed to Priſon by one of the</hi> Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, <hi>who ſeeing him to be a very proper young Man, in the Flower of his Age, and imagining that he might quickly Overthrow him by the ſin of the Fleſh, found means to have a Woman conveyed to his</hi> Bed, <hi>who being repelled by him, and the Enemy ſeeing that the practiſe took no effect, but came to be known, not only to all that were in the Priſon, but alſo to many others abroad, to the Commendation of the Prieſts Chaſtity, and honor of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalick Religion, he was ſo incenſed againſt him, That he caus'd him to be hang'd up, firſt by the</hi> Privy Parts (<hi>which he made to be</hi> Pierced <hi>in divers places with</hi> hot Irons) <hi>and after by the Hands, untill he was half dead, and then called in many to ſee his ſaid Privy parts inſtamed and rankled with the Burning of the hot Irons, ſaying unto them, after they were gone forth again, Behold this Chast Prieſt, how he hath dreſſed, and ſpoiled himſelf with naughty Women. And not content therewith, cauſed him alſo to be Arraigned, and Executed for being a Prieſt, without having any other Matter againſt him: Which kind of Cruelty, tending to the Overthrow both of Soul, Body, Honor, and all, can hardly be matched with any Example of the Old Heathen Perſecutors of the Primitive Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far that <hi>effronted Jeſuite</hi> (for ſo the <hi>Author</hi> appears to be) and indeed, Could any thing be deviſed more <hi>horrid,</hi> but withall more <hi>improbable,</hi> and remote from Truth? yet hereby we ſee <hi>Cellier,</hi> and her <hi>Inſpirers,</hi> wanted not <hi>Preſidents</hi> for their Fiction, their Party having ſo long <hi>inur'd</hi> themſelves to Forging Untruths, that now they think they may lawfully <hi>Lie</hi> by <hi>Preſcription.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having therefore Vindicated, not ſo much my <hi>Self,</hi> as <hi>Truth,</hi> and the Honor of my Country, from that Notorious Slander, I ſhall take this Opportunity to wipe off ſome <hi>other Aſperſions</hi> that have altogether as <hi>groundleſly</hi> been raiſed by the Popiſh Faction, and other <hi>ill people,</hi> to the prejudice of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Month of <hi>May</hi> laſt, there was a Publick Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon me, in a Thing called, <hi>The Domeſtick Intelligence;</hi> Suggeſting, as if I had received 500 <hi>l.</hi> of one <hi>Blunden,</hi> for my being concerned in the Murder of Juſtice <hi>Godfrey.</hi> The Truth of which whole matter was thus—Some ſhort time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt Diſcovery of the <hi>Plot,</hi> I did, by the Order of one <hi>Fowler</hi> a Prieſt, that was a kind of Steward to one Mr.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52465:6"/>
               <hi>Ployden</hi> then in <hi>France,</hi> receive of Mr. <hi>Blunden</hi> of <hi>Baſingſtoke</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire</hi> (then utterly a ſtranger to me) 90 <hi>l.</hi> Fifty pounds whereof I ſoon after paid away to a Merchant in <hi>London,</hi> to be Tranſmitted to the ſaid <hi>Ployden,</hi> and the reſt to the ſaid <hi>Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi> Now afterwards when I had made my Diſcovery, and was generally <hi>Talked</hi> of, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Blunden,</hi> in Diſcourſe with one <hi>Fowler</hi> an Apothecary in <hi>London,</hi> happened to ſay, That he had once <hi>ſeen me,</hi> and paid me ſome Money, and he wiſh'd it were not Imploy'd in the <hi>Plot,</hi> or Words to that purpoſe; Long after this, a falling out (as 'tis ſaid) happening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Mr. <hi>Blunden</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Fowler</hi> the Apothecary; the latter having, it ſeems, heard talk of one <hi>Blunden,</hi> a Popiſh Prieſt, that uſed to frequent <hi>Newgate,</hi> and manage <hi>Catholick Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works,</hi> &amp;c. did thereupon (whether out of <hi>Revenge,</hi> or pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on a Miſtake, I know not) give Information againſt this Mr. <hi>Blunden</hi> as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and that he Confeſſed to him that he paid me 500 <hi>l.</hi> for the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> &amp;c. Hereupon I was called before His Majeſties moſt Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Privy-Council, to whom I related the Premiſes, How that <hi>Blunden</hi> was a <hi>Stranger</hi> to me; that I never ſaw him but once, and then received 90 <hi>l.</hi> of him on the Account aforeſaid But, moſt truly deny'd, that I ever received of him, or any other Perſon whatſoever 500 <hi>l.</hi> or any other Sum of Money for my being Concerned about that Horrid Murder. And the ſaid Mr. <hi>Blunden</hi> being ſent for up by a Meſſenger, did deny that he ever ſpoke any <hi>ſuch words</hi> relating to me, but only that once he, by Order, paid unto me the ſaid 90 <hi>l.</hi> and, upon Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, was found to be <hi>A good Proteſtant, and a very honeſt Man;</hi> Whereupon, the matter being referred to the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> he was there ſoon after Diſcharged But the <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary,</hi> who occaſion'd all this <hi>Noiſe,</hi> and cauſeleſs Trouble, was ordered to find <hi>Sureties</hi> for the Good Behaviour; And the Author of the <hi>Domeſtick Intelligence</hi> did <hi>Retract</hi> his News, and Ask my Pardon; And perceiving he did it through <hi>Miſinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> and not with <hi>Deſign,</hi> I did paſs it by, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him further Trouble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Papiſts buz abroad Reports, as if what I have done were for <hi>Profit,</hi> or that I had got ſome <hi>Great Advantages</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming an Evidence. This is the Common Lerry of their <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets;</hi> Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> has a Touch of it, in that moſt Audacious and Seditious Expreſſion (in the Poſtſcript) <hi>Whenſoever His Majeſty pleaſes to make it as ſafe and Honorable to ſpeak Truth, as it is Apparent it hath been Gainful and Meritorious to do the Contrary,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52465:7"/>In Anſwer to which, I ſhall only ſay, That as I owe my Life to His Majeſties <hi>Mercy,</hi> ſo I am freely ready to expend the whole Remainder of it in his <hi>Service:</hi> And as I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, That when I have done all I can, I have done but my <hi>Duty;</hi> So with all <hi>Thankfulneſs</hi> I do own, That His Majeſty has Graciouſly been pleaſed to <hi>Encourage</hi> my poor Endeavours, To whoſe <hi>good pleaſure</hi> I contentedly ſubmit my ſelf; Only to confute theſe Malitious Clamors of <hi>Extraordinary Gains,</hi> am ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to Declare this Truth, That from my firſt Diſcovery to this day, I never had, or received any <hi>Allowance, Penſion, Salary, Place Sum of Money,</hi> or other <hi>Advantage</hi> whatſoever, ſave only the Sum of 30 <hi>l</hi> Ordered me ſoon after my coming out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Now, if it be Conſidered into what hard Circumſtances this my Honeſt Diſcovery had brought me, That I have loſt a Conſiderable and Conſtant <hi>Imploy</hi> from Her Majeſty; Nay, that I have loſt my <hi>whole Trade</hi> and Livelihood, which lay altogether amongſt <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts.</hi> That I have now ſpent well nigh Two years in the Service of the Publick, which occaſionally has taken up <hi>moſt of my time,</hi> and neceſſitated me to very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Expences,</hi> and the neglect of my Private Concerns, to the great hazard of Ruining my ſelf and Family: All this, I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered, I conceive 30 <hi>l.</hi> cannot be thought any ſuch <hi>enviable sum,</hi> that any need upbraid me with the <hi>Gains</hi> I have made by my Evidence; Though yet, to me, the Gains (but in a far different ſence) are invaluable. Having, I bleſs God, gain'd the Quiet of my Conſcience, before miſerably diſtracted with being Privy to that Horrid Murder (The only Rack and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which I ever ſuffer'd.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another <hi>Aſperſion,</hi> is, That I have charg'd ſome as Popiſh Prieſts, whom I could not <hi>prove</hi> to be ſuch, and particularly one <hi>Geldon</hi> But this I do avow is abſolutely falſe: For, as ſeveral Prieſts, viz. <hi>Parry, Knapper,</hi> and others, have been by me Diſcover'd, and are Legally <hi>Convicted</hi> (though I have not yet received one <hi>farthing</hi> on that Account of the Rewards pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in His Majeſties <hi>Royal Proclamations</hi>) ſo I never Tax'd any but whom I certainly knew to be Prieſts. And as for <hi>Geldon,</hi> alias <hi>Bacon,</hi> I did Diſcover and Apprehend him in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> laſt (he having juſt before been in Cure of a deſperate. <hi>Pox</hi>) who thereupon was Committed to <hi>Newgate:</hi> Nor was it my Fault that he was not Proſecuted, having been ready to Attend to give Evidence; and ſince, underſtanding that he was got out upon <hi>Bail,</hi> I did my ſelf, the Laſt Seſſions, prefer an <hi>Indictment</hi> againſt him, which is found by the Grand Jury; and I am ready (as I doubt not with good Evidence) to prove it upon him, Let him appear if he dare.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52465:7"/>Another damnable Scandal they have broached, which, tho it principally be level'd at Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> as if he under pretence of ſearching for <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and ſeizing <hi>Popiſh Trinckets,</hi> ſhould take away <hi>Money, Plate,</hi> and other things of value from the Owners, and <hi>Necklaces</hi> of <hi>Pearl</hi> for <hi>Beads;</hi> yet ſince I very frequently went along with him, it does obliquely <hi>reflect</hi> on me, and I cannot but do that worthy Gentleman the right to juſtify him againſt ſuch a moſt falſe groundleſs and malicious ſlander: I do therefore <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in the preſence of God,</hi> and ſhall be ready to Atteſt on my Oath, that whenſoever I attended him in <hi>Searches,</hi> (which was almoſt every day,) I never could diſcern in him the leaſt inclination to any ſuch <hi>baſe practice;</hi> but that to the contrary he behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as a good Chriſtian and <hi>juſt Magistrate;</hi> for wherever we came what <hi>Money</hi> was found was left in the Owners poſſeſſion, and as for <hi>Chalices</hi> and <hi>Pixes</hi> (of <hi>Plate</hi>) belonging to <hi>Prieſts</hi> and uſed in their <hi>Maſs,</hi> or for keeping <hi>Holy Oyl,</hi> &amp;c. We did indeed batter or break them to pieces, but always returned all the pieces to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, But their <hi>Copes</hi> and <hi>Prieſtly Veſtments, Superstitious Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, Habit</hi> of <hi>Monks</hi> belonging to their peculiar <hi>Orders,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Trumpery,</hi> we did ſometimes take away and cauſe them to be publickly burnt never making any advantage thereof. And as for <hi>Books</hi> being ſometimes too numerous to be immediately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, they were laid up (each mans by themſelves) in places where thoſe they belonged to, might by their Friends have <hi>Acceſs</hi> to them, and ſuch as were not <hi>Prohibited</hi> by <hi>Law</hi> were ready to be returned. And as to any <hi>Necklaces</hi> of <hi>Pearl,</hi> reported to be by him taken away, I am more than conſident the ſame is as errand a Lie, as that he thought one <hi>Bednigfield,</hi> whom he took at <hi>Newmark</hi>— to have been the ſame <hi>Beding field,</hi> who dyed in the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> for he well knew it was another Man, but likewiſe was not ignorant that 'twas not unuſual for two or more <hi>Prieſts</hi> to go by the ſame Name, which yet many times doth in truth belong to none of them. And if Sir <hi>William</hi> had committed any ſuch ill Acts, why did not the People injured or ſome of them <hi>Indict</hi> him, or bring their <hi>Actions,</hi> (his being a <hi>Juſtice</hi> was no <hi>Protection,</hi>) or why at leaſt did not they forthwith complain to the King and Council, rather than Right themſelves in <hi>N. T's Lying Intelligence?</hi> But alas, they well knew theſe ſtories would not indure the <hi>Teſt,</hi> only might ſerve to raiſe ſcurvy apprehenſions among ſome ſilly inconſiderate People.</p>
            <p>And therefore to ſhew Sir <hi>Williams</hi> innocence, integrity, and kind dealing in theſe Caſes, I ſhall at preſent only give the following in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance amongſt many others, which <hi>to my knowledge</hi> are true. When we took <hi>Napper</hi> a <hi>Priest,</hi> and now a <hi>Condemned Traitor</hi> in <hi>Newgate;</hi> we found in his Chamber about 50 pieces of <hi>Gold,</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parcels of <hi>Silver,</hi> two <hi>Silver Tobaco-Boxes</hi> and other ſuch things to the value of above 100 <hi>l.</hi> as I verily believe, and there was no body preſent but Sir <hi>William</hi> and his Company. Now here
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52465:8"/>was a convenient <hi>bootty,</hi> which if there had been any ſuch beſe avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious deſign, might have cleverly been carried off by colour of ſeizing it as appertaining to a <hi>Traitor.</hi> But Sir <hi>William</hi> was ſo far from offering any ſuch thing, that he called to Mr. <hi>Napper,</hi> and told him, Sir, <hi>You muſt to Priſon, and poſſibly may have occaſion for your Money; therefore take this Cabinet</hi> (pointing to one that ſtood there,) <hi>and put all your Treaſure therein; and either take it with you, or repoſite it in ſuch hands as you can truſt.</hi> Now, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely is it, that he who was ſo <hi>generouſly juſt</hi> and kind to a known Prieſt, ſhould be ſo pitifully injurious to Ladies of Quality, or any other People far leſs obnoxious, and more capable to right them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>This I thought my ſelf bound in Conſcience to ſay of that Honourable Gentleman, (for whether he be <hi>living</hi> or dead, I know not,) and do heartily wiſh, That all <hi>Miniſters of Juſtice</hi> throughout <hi>England</hi> were as diligently zeaſous in diſcharge of their Truſt, for the finding out and puniſhing all lurking <hi>Jeſuits, Popiſh Priests,</hi> and ſuch like Traiterous Vermin; for if they be not vigorouſly proſecuted, his Majeſties ſacred Life and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot be <hi>ſafe,</hi> but they will be perpetually carrying on their <hi>Helliſh Plot,</hi> and creating freſh Diſturbances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is yet another Aſperſion, which is ſo <hi>vain</hi> and incredible, that I could ſcarce believe it ſhould enter into the Heads of any reaſonable people, did I not to my amazement often hear it Reported, which is, <hi>That I am ſtill a Papiſt.</hi> Now as to this, I know not what <hi>words</hi> I can uſe will be effectual to Confute ſuch a ridiculous ſuſpicion, if the <hi>Things</hi> I have done, ſo clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtating the contrary, cannot <hi>convince</hi> them; I ſhall therefore only ſay, That as Reflections on the horrid Murder of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> and the villany of the Prieſts urging the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> on't, did (when I came calmly to <hi>Conſider it</hi>) raiſe at firſt an <hi>Averſion</hi> in me to that <hi>Bloody Religion,</hi> ſo by the Grace of God, the <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> which the now Reverend Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> and other <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> were charitably pleaſed to uſe to me, fully convinc'd me of the Falſhood, Abſurdity, and Superſtitions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and on the other ſide, of the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>ſoundneſs</hi> of the Proteſtant Doctrine, and it's agreeableneſs to the <hi>ſacred Word</hi> of God, and all the glorious Ends of Chriſtianity, whereupon heartily, unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and on grounds fully ſatisfying my Conſcience, I did caſt my ſelf into the Arms of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and have without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering in the leaſt, ſtrictly adhered to her <hi>Communion</hi> in all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Exerciſes of Religion, and do reſolve, by the help of Almighty God, therein to continue to the laſt moment of my life. Nor can it be any but <hi>Papists,</hi> and their Inſtruments, that would broach this Fable; who do it only to render me ſuſpected to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and thereby ſully the eſteem of my Evidence againſt <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> And therefore if hereafter any ſhall maliciouſly ſpread ſuch <hi>ſtories,</hi> I ſhall not be wanting to vindicate my ſelf, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52465:8"/>puniſh their Extravagance by ſuch Remedies as the <hi>Law</hi> allows me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Having thus wip'd off the Scandals of profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, I muſt now take leave to rectifie certain Miſtakes of a <hi>Friend</hi> in a Pamphlet entituled, <hi>The Narrative of</hi> William Boys: The Pen-man of which has committed ſome Errors, or at leaſt repreſented things ſo as they may be liable to Miſconſtructions; as <hi>p.</hi> 5, and 6. where he ſeems with many words to tell a ſtory, as if I had not made the diſcovery of <hi>Godfries</hi> Murther till the <hi>12th</hi> or <hi>13th</hi> of <hi>January;</hi> and that he the ſaid Mr. <hi>Boys</hi> was the <hi>firſt man</hi> in the World that I revealed it to. Whereas in truth I had many days before acquainted both the <hi>Committee of Lords,</hi> and the <hi>Lords of the Council</hi> therewith; and <hi>Green, Berry,</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> were thereupon in Priſon, as before herein is ſet forth. And the real Truth of the matter that he talks of is only thus: That ſometime <hi>after</hi> I had made ſuch diſcovery, the cloſeneſs of the Priſon (though I were uſed otherwiſe with Civility enough) occaſioned my falling <hi>ſick,</hi> and being in a Feaver, I might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps (as is uſual in ſuch caſes) being then Light-headed, uſe ſome extravagant expreſſions; and in that condition, when Queſtions were askt me, might (as he obſerves <hi>p.</hi> 5.) <hi>never anſwer to the purpoſe.</hi> Whereupon Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> being knowe to be very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted and familiar with me, was ordered by the <hi>Lords of the Committee</hi> on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> to come to me, and keep me Company; which he did for ſeveral days: And as ſoon as I reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered any competent degree of <hi>health,</hi> and was able to talk rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, I did declare to him the manner of Sir <hi>Edm. Godfry</hi>'s Murther, and confirm what before my ſickneſs I had diſcovered to the <hi>Lords.</hi> And though what he did was by Order, yet I acknowledge my Obligations to Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> for his Society and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe,</hi> which was very acceptable to me in that condition; nor were the Lords wanting to ſatisfy him for his <hi>time</hi> expended in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending me, but became (as appears in his Paper <hi>p.</hi> 7.) ſuitors to his Majeſty, on the <hi>29th.</hi> of the ſame <hi>January</hi> for 30 <hi>l.</hi> for him, which I underſtand he received, and I ſuppoſe will not deny it to have been a bountifull <hi>Reward</hi> for about 19 days going up and down.</p>
            <p>But from this Diſcourſe of his I am apt to believe the Contrivers of <hi>Celliers</hi> Libel might take the <hi>Hint</hi> to time that Story of her hearing me Rack'd, for he having publiſh'd, that he came to me the Tenth of <hi>January,</hi> and that I did not make any Confeſſion till ſome daies after; theſe ſubtle Forgers lay the ſcene of their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing Tragedy on the 9, 10, and 11 daies, as you have heard, to make it ſeem the more probable that my Confeſſion proceeded from ſome ill uſage. I would not hereby be miſunderſtood to inſinuate, That Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> had any <hi>bad Deſign,</hi> or were in Confederacy with <hi>Gellier</hi> and her Gang, for I have far better thoughts of him, but only I ſay, 'tis probable they might take the advantage thence to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52465:9"/>ſix the buſineſs preciſely on the Ninth of <hi>January.</hi> But as to the cruelty of <hi>Racking</hi> Mr. <hi>Boyce, p.</hi> 8. does very honeſtly and juſtly atteſt that there was no ſuch thing, which might, were there occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, be confirm'd by twenty others. <hi>P.</hi> 10. He tells the World, <hi>That he took me and my Wife home to his Houſe for a Month;</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my old Friend has no intent (as he has little <hi>reaſon</hi>) by theſe words to <hi>upbraid me</hi> with his kindneſs, 'Tis true, we did lie at her Houſe about a Month, but as in that time we provided a great part of our <hi>Diet;</hi> ſo at our going away, I gave Mrs. <hi>Boyce</hi> 5 <hi>l.</hi> for the trouble we had given their Houſe, and never heard but they were therewith well ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>At the end of the ſame Page, 'tis ſaid, <hi>That my Wife her ſelf went to her ſiſter</hi> Sherburn, <hi>a zealous Papist,</hi> and cunningly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd her that the time was now come to be Revenged upon Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> for being inſtrument in the diſcovery of the Murder of Sir <hi>E.G.</hi> for that I and he were faln out. As to this, <hi>First,</hi> I do not underſtand, that if we had been indeed faln out, how this could have contributed to their taking <hi>Revenge</hi> on Mr. <hi>Boyce,</hi> for I bleſs God though we had a long acquaintance, yet we never had any <hi>dangerous ſecrets</hi> between us, whereby either party might be able to <hi>prejudice</hi> the other, if he ſhould have ſo much <hi>ill nature,</hi> or <hi>malice</hi> as to endeavour it. <hi>Secondly,</hi> If my Wife did ſo <hi>cunningly</hi> inform her Siſter of this, I ſuppoſe 'twas <hi>ſecretly;</hi> and if ſo, how came Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> to know of it? And <hi>thirdly,</hi> If he did know her to be of ſo treacherous and diſſembling a Spirit (for no Neighbour or Friend could ſhew more kindneſs than ſhe alwaies did to Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> and all his Family,) 'tis a wonder that he would after this, ſend for her to his Houſe, and deſire her to ſit up two daies and a night with his Wife in her ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 15. Mr. <hi>Boyce</hi> ſeems to take it ill, becauſe I gave him ſome notice that he was to be examined in <hi>January</hi> laſt; I did not tell him <hi>what it was about,</hi> but this it is to be offended with me for not being a <hi>Conjurer,</hi> for I knew it not my ſelf; nor do I remember that I ſaid any thing to him, of his having talkt at a ſtrange rate of things <hi>of high and great Concernment,</hi> having no reaſon, that I know of, to uſe ſuch an Expreſſion. In a word, as I have heen long and intimately acquainted with Mr. <hi>Boyce,</hi> ſo I ſhall never be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful for any kindneſſes. But there are ſome people in the World that ſully their <hi>Courteſies</hi> with an <hi>importune oſtentation,</hi> who never think their <hi>Obligations</hi> cancel'd, and upbraid their Friends with their good Offices ſo much and ſo long that they loſe almoſt all their luſter, and the <hi>Cackling</hi> proves more troubleſome than the <hi>Egg</hi> was valuable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> A Neighbour of mine, one Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> being queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for ſome words, whilſt this was preparing for the Preſs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to have been ſpoken by him, though I did no more than what I was obliged unto both in <hi>Duty,</hi> and for my own <hi>ſafety</hi> in that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, yet ſome people have miſ-repreſented it, and thence raiſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52465:9"/>falſe Reports to my prejudice, and therefore I ſhall preſume to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex an Account thereof, being thus, On <hi>Thurſday, Sept.</hi> 23. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, I heard a Rumour, That the ſaid Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> on the <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> before had to his Journey-man ſpoken words of <hi>dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence;</hi> and that a Boy related to me, and boarding in my Houſe heard him, and did <hi>Report</hi> it. Hereupon I having a long time known the ſaid Mr. <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and never obſerved any thing by him, but that he was a very <hi>Civil peaceable</hi> man, took the Boy to task, threatning him for reporting ſuch falſe things, enough to ruin an honeſt man, the Boy perſiſted that he did hear him ſay ſuch words; and deſired me to ask the Journey-man, whether it were not true; which I did, who ſeemed to own that there was ſome ſuch like words paſs'd between them, though not the ſame that the Boy (who heard them at ſome diſtance) had reported, but that they were qualified with certain other circumſtances and expreſſions. Hereupon the noiſe encreaſing, and ſeveral perſons directing their diſcourſe to me about it, though the man were a Neighbour, and one I had a kindneſs for; yet where my <hi>King</hi> is concern'd, I know <hi>no Friend,</hi> and had it been never ſo near a <hi>Relation,</hi> I ſhould have thought my ſelf bound in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give notice of it, That the matter might be examined; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly I did acquaint the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Sunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> one of the principal Secretaries of State, with what I had heard reported, who commanded me to attend the Council, and there it was ordered that Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> ſhould be taken into a <hi>Meſſengers</hi> hands, and on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> laſt the matter being heard before the Honorable Board, I did acquaint their Lordſhips, That <hi>I knew nothing of my own knowledge of the words, for I heard them not. That Mr.</hi> Salisbury <hi>had been divers years my Neighbour, and had alwaies behav'd himſelf very civilly amongſt us, and that I had alwaies lookt upon him as an honeſt man and good Subject.</hi> Then the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> were Examined, and the words appearing to have been in part miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the Boy, and the occaſion and circumſtances of ſpeaking them being declared by the other Witneſs, it was lookt upon but as <hi>impertinent Chat,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Salisbury</hi> was diſcharged. In which affair I am confident no diſcreet man or good Subject will blame me: For beſides my Obligations by my Allegiance, my particular circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances oblig'd me to it, for how did, or do I ſtill know, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port might be fomented by ſome Papiſts under-hand, and eſpecially Addreſt to me, that if I had not ſpeedily informed Authority, they might have had matter of Accuſation againſt me?</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude the whole with this ſolemn <hi>Proteſtation</hi> in the preſence of Almighty God, That I was never in any kind <hi>Rack'd</hi> or put to Torture by any perſons during my Confinement; nor by any threatnings, or other ill means induced to the <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> I have made; and that what I have ſet forth thereof, and the Evidence I have given thereof againſt <hi>Green, Bury,</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> or againſt any other perſon or perſons relating thereunto, or to the <hi>Plot</hi> in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or for being <hi>Prieſts,</hi> is true; and that I have not been ſway'd therein by Malice, Revenge, hopes of profit, or any other ſiniſter end whatſoever. In Teſtimony whereof I have hereunto ſubſcribed my Hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Miles Prance.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:52465:10"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THe World I conceive is by this time pretty well ſatisfied in the Character of the famous Mrs. <hi>Cellier;</hi> yet to divert the Reader, we would have him take a little further notice of her two Cardinal vertues, <hi>Ambitious Impudence,</hi> and a prodigious knack of <hi>Counterfeiting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Impudence (to wave the Hiſtory of her lewd Life) her whole Libel is a ſufficient Inſtance, particularly <hi>p.</hi> 29. where ſhe has the Forehead to ſay of the Lords of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council, <hi>That they askt her many Trepanning Queſtions to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare her;</hi> What a mighty Woman would this be counted, as if their <hi>Honours</hi> would turn <hi>Treppans</hi> to enſnare (forſooth) ſuch a <hi>Draggle-tail'd Prattle-box;</hi> So <hi>p.</hi> 35. ſhe intimates her politick of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiouſneſs, <hi>That ſhe carried the names of four Perſons to the</hi> D. <hi>in hopes to have them put into the Commiſſion of the Peace, which might conduce much to the breaking of the meaſures of the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>—[that is, no doubt, being Tranſlated out of the <hi>Catholick Cant</hi> into honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi>—Conduce much to diverting the proſecution againſt <hi>Popiſh Traitors.</hi>] Now was not ſhe (think you) a rare Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman to be a Juſtice-maker? In purſuance of which vain rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Humour, after ſhe was queſtioned for her Libel, ſhe had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to quarrel with the King's <hi>Meſſenger</hi> that diſcover'd it, For having ſome time before ſtopt a <hi>Weekly Pamphlet</hi> of Intelligence, intended to have been publiſh'd by Mr. <hi>Roger L'Eſtrange;</hi> Saying (as I am credibly inform'd) that the ſaid Meſſenger <hi>did very ill in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the ſame</hi> (though he acted only purſuant to his Majeſties Royal Proclamation) and further told him, That <hi>ſhe would have it Reviv'd, and go on, for it would be a thing of great uſe;</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Mr. <hi>L'Eſtrange</hi> very familiarly, and pretending then to ſend her Imps <hi>Grange</hi> and <hi>Sing</hi> up and down to him; Though for all her vain Boaſting, it cannot (I think) be imagin'd that ſo worthy a Gentleman, and ſo much a Proteſtant, as he has ſhown himſelf by his late Learned Pamphlets; And one that is, (as I am told) of late a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace, would have any Correſpondence with ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious <hi>Popiſh Baggage,</hi> eſpecially ſince his <hi>Marriage,</hi> for before it might lie in <hi>her way</hi> perhaps (had he been willing) to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him.</p>
            <p>As for her Counterfeiting Intrigues and <hi>Sham-tricks,</hi> her whole Life has been but one <hi>continued ſcene of Legerdemain,</hi> ſo that all the <hi>Guſmans,</hi> and <hi>Gypſies</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> are but <hi>Novices</hi> to her, and therefore moſt fit ſhe was to be choſen <hi>Tutreſs</hi> to the <hi>Younglings</hi> of St. <hi>Omers.</hi> It would be too tedious to reckon up half the <hi>Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems</hi> ſhe has invented in her daies; only becauſe the Adventure of the <hi>ſanguine Bladder</hi> will do well in after Ages to be join'd to that of the <hi>Meal-tub,</hi> I ſhall here oblige the World with a brief Relation on't.</p>
            <p>After ſhe had lately receiv'd her Sentence to ſtand 3 days on the <hi>Pillory,</hi> &amp;c. Some of the Officers of the <hi>Colledge</hi> wherein her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip at preſent reſides, knowing her to be a Woman of <hi>Intregue,</hi> and reſolving to obſerve how ſhe would behave her ſelf, gave her intimation on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>16th.</hi> inſtant, that ſhe was to ſtand the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52465:10"/>
               <hi>next day.</hi> Hereupon, to prevent the worſt, ſhe got in her <hi>Armour</hi> of defence, and <hi>a Cap, of Maintainance</hi> made of <hi>trusty Bull-hide,</hi> (the very ſame which her <hi>brother Giles</hi> lately made uſe of on the like occaſion;) but with all provided her ſelf of a <hi>Vomit,</hi> ſo that (having tim'd the taking of it conveniently,) when they (to carry on the humour) came up the next morning as if to call her down; ſhe was moſt buſily <hi>caſting</hi> up her Accounts, as if ſhe would have <hi>diſgorg'd</hi> a Thouſand <hi>Sham-Plots,</hi> and proteſted it was a diſtemper had <hi>juſt then</hi> ſeiz'd her, they <hi>ſmil'd</hi> at the pretty contrivance and left her; but when ſhe found they had but made a fool of her, and caus'd her to take her <hi>Phyſick a day too ſoon</hi> and troubled her ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack to no purpoſe, ſhe could with all her heart have <hi>ſpewed</hi> in their Chaps.</p>
            <p>However underſtanding that afternoon that ſhe was to <hi>ſtand</hi> in good earneſt on the morrow, being <hi>Saturday,</hi> ſhe knew there was no repeating the ſame <hi>Artifice,</hi> and ſo ſtudied <hi>another,</hi> declaring her ſelf <hi>with Child,</hi> and every minute expecting the unlucky hour, when ſhe ſhould bleſs <hi>Newgate</hi> with a Catholick Babe: This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd very improbable in a perſon of her <hi>reverend years,</hi> and one Midwife being ſent to her retorn'd a <hi>Non Inventus</hi> on her Belly; but another being call'd at her importunity, ſhe dealt ſo, effectually with a <hi>ſmall Argument in hand,</hi> and promiſes to prefer her to be Midwife to a certain great Lady, that the good Woman was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with to juſtify her pregnancy. The Cheat being thus far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, on the <hi>Saturday</hi> morning, her <hi>Maid</hi> (fit for ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs) very early cry'd out to the Keepers, and acquainted them that her Miſtreſs was <hi>extream Ill;</hi> and ſome time after Captain <hi>R.</hi> ſending her up word, that ſhe muſt <hi>prepare to go forth</hi> to the Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Engine, ſhe, in <hi>dying tone</hi> replyed, that they might do what they would with her, but ſhe was <hi>not able to ſtir out of her Bed;</hi> whereupon he ordered 3 or 4 honeſt Women to go up and dreſs her, charging them to handle her with all <hi>tenderneſs,</hi> and let the Maid be by, for he knew ſhe would be ready enough to ſwear he had <hi>Rackt and Tortur'd her.</hi> They accordingly with much adoe <hi>Accoutred</hi> her, but then ſhe would not ſtir a foot, ſo two men very <hi>gingerly</hi> brought her down, and would have ſeated her in a Chair; but ſhe tumbled her ſelf all along on the floor, and roar'd out, <hi>O my back; hold my back, hold my ſides, I am in Labour, call ſome Women, for modeſty ſake let the Men be gone, uſe not a Woman in my Condition more barbarouſly then Heathens; more Savagely than Turks and Indians, &amp;c.</hi> By this time ſome of her female popiſh <hi>Gang</hi> were got about her, and all agreed, that ſhe was <hi>juſt on point of delivery;</hi> nay ſo far had ſhe deluded them, that 'tis ſaid, ſome of them went to a Magiſtrate and offer'd to <hi>ſwear</hi> it; and the Shreiffs Officers ſhe had ſo ſatisfied that they were loth to meddle with carrying her abroad.</p>
            <p>She <hi>bellow'd</hi> out ſo hideouſly that one of the Popiſh Prieſts was over-heard to ſay <hi>ſhe over-acts it,</hi> and ſome of the ſpectators thought her poſſeſt, and were ready to call Father <hi>Marſhall</hi> to try (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the laudable practice of their Church) his skill in <hi>Conjuring</hi> and <hi>exorciſing</hi> upon her; but others more prudent alledg'd, that <hi>Monks were better vers'd in raiſing Evil Spirits, than laying them,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52465:11"/>and more fit to put the Devil into ſuch a Woman than caſt him out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt after a world of <hi>Groanings</hi> (worſe than thoſe of a Soul in Purgatory) and a thouſand moſt bewitching <hi>wry faces,</hi> an able Phyſician and ſeveral diſcreet Women being ſent for, they ſearch'd her ſo narrowly, that they diſcover'd the <hi>whole Cheat,</hi> and found that the good Lady was no more with <hi>Bearn</hi> than the <hi>Town-bull,</hi> but only having over-night privately gotten a <hi>Bladder of Blood,</hi> had uſed her skill in creating the neceſſary <hi>ſymptomes,</hi> and preparing certain <hi>Clotts</hi> of it, and put them into her Body, (ſome of which ſort deſign'd for a freſh ſupply, were alſo found elſewhere about her.)</p>
            <p>Thus (for I would not grate <hi>modeſt Ears</hi> with inſiſting on ſo fulſome a ſtory,) our politick Madam was delivered only of a <hi>Moon-Calfe</hi> or (if you pleaſe) a few <hi>Abortive Blackamores;</hi> nor is it any wonder, that the <hi>Birth</hi> ſhould prove <hi>prodigious,</hi> for almoſt a Twelve month ago, coming in a Coach from <hi>Whitehall</hi> (when ſhe thought ſhe might ſhortly be Hang'd,) ſhe very ſolemnly declared to an Officer that came with her, that juſt then <hi>ſhe Quickned;</hi> and ſince a <hi>Lioneſs</hi> is ſaid to go with young 10 years, why may we not allow 13 or 14 months to ſuch a <hi>teeming Bear</hi> of fifty odd.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sham</hi> being thus detected, ſhe was carried to the <hi>place of Exaltation.</hi> How ſhe behav'd her ſelf there every body knows; and though ſhe were ſufficiently defended by a numerous <hi>Guard</hi> and her own <hi>Armour,</hi> ſo that really ſhe receiv'd no hurt from the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, yet ſhe pretended her ſelf <hi>half-Martyr'd;</hi> and 'tis ſaid, had the ſilly confidence to ſend divers of the <hi>Stones</hi> that were caſt at her to <hi>New-Market;</hi> which, if ſhe did, I verily believe the <hi>Return</hi> ſcarce anſwered the <hi>Fraight.</hi> However, to carry on the Cheat at home, though ſhe were up early the next Morning (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sunday</hi>) and briskly <hi>walking up and down</hi> her Chamber, and buſie in <hi>writing Letters, &amp;c.</hi> yet about Noon, (when ſhe began to expect <hi>Viſiters,</hi>) ſhe put off her Clothes and went to Bed, lying all the Afternoon roaring and complaining of her terrible <hi>bruiſes,</hi> and that ſhe was not able to <hi>ſtir;</hi> which rais'd ſuch Compaſſion in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of devout <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that they could not forbear <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering their Plants;</hi> nor ſhe (ſure) chuſe but <hi>ſmile in conceit</hi> (amongſt all her outward Lamentations,) to think, how neatly ſhe impos'd upon their fooliſh Credulity.</p>
            <p>Theſe matters of <hi>Fact</hi> are notoriouſly true, and ready to be juſtified; and therefore I would entreat all <hi>modeſt Papiſts</hi> (if there be any ſuch) to reflect, what a <hi>Championeſs</hi> they have got, and what an honour ſhe is like to prove to their Cauſe: A Perſon who makes no Conſcience of any thing ſhe <hi>does</hi> or <hi>ſays,</hi> who <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes</hi> and <hi>denies</hi> things with the ſame breath; and <hi>mocks</hi> God and <hi>abuſes</hi> the World with counterfeiting Childbirth-pains, and this by ſuch <hi>immodeſt Practiſes</hi> as are a <hi>reproach to Nature,</hi> and a <hi>ſhame</hi> to all her <hi>Sex.</hi> In a word, What <hi>wickedneſs</hi> might not ſuch a Creature be fit to <hi>attempt?</hi> What <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> not apt to engage in? What <hi>Villany</hi> not ready to execute? Whoſe <hi>Head</hi> is giddy with <hi>Ambition;</hi> her <hi>Heart</hi> rancour'd with <hi>Malice;</hi> her <hi>Tongue</hi> tipt with <hi>Lies;</hi> her very <hi>Soul</hi> a <hi>Juggle,</hi> and her <hi>Complexion</hi> all over <hi>Braſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
